hey guys matt ritman here
um i've been creating a glock model and
um i'm going through and animating it
and showing how it works and i just
wanted to share a few things with you
guys as far as what i've been learning
throughout throughout the process and uh
today i'm going to show you how i rigged
the the magazine how the bullets are fed
through it and
all that good stuff so why don't we go
ahead and jump in
so inside cinema 4d
we've got our model here and i'm not
going to be showing you how i modeled
stuff that's that's a separate tutorial
but
we've got the spring we've got the
follower that pushes the bullets through
the magazine the bullet and the magazine
housing itself
so let's start with compressing the
spring down and then we'll kind of go
from from there so
and my spring is
really just
a helix object that i turned into a
spline and
adjusted the spline so that i could get
a custom shape out of it it's more
square than
than circular so
um and to compress this we're going to
use a squash and stretch deformer
so if you click on spline your spline
and you click under deformers
hold down shift and click squash and
stretch it'll make that a child of your
spline
and we want to compress it starting from
the bottom so we need to set the bottom
of our squash and stretch to zero
and then we need to move this to the
base
just like that
and our top here it needs to be set to
the top of the spring so
just pull this up
now if we change our factor
you'll see that it compresses down but
it also comes out and expands and we
don't want that so
just turn to expand down to zero
we won't be using that
and you'll see we're getting some kind
of funky bending here and that's just
because of our positioning of our squash
and stretch here so if we pull this down
we'll get the bottom to be more
more aligned here
so just like that
and the top
if we just kind of
play with our top setting here that
looks good
so
there we have it just by changing this
factor
we can change the uh
expansion of the spring
and
it would be nice to actually set this up
on its own slider so we don't have to go
into the squash and stretch and change
that right there so
um we're going to start by creating some
user data for
the
the topmost object in our scene the
magazine
so click on magazine
and
click user data manage user data
and go ahead and add a group
and pull this group out of the default
one
and just name this
controls
oops
controls so and then we need to add some
data to the control group so click add
data
and just name this one magazine feeder
and data type floats correct and
interface we want to use we want a
slider so change this to float slider
and that'll give us the nice slider
and just hit ok
and now under magazine we've got a
controls tab
with our slider
so go ahead and drag this to the
viewport
and you'll see if i click off this the
magazine object it'll go away
and to get that to stay there on the
viewport
just right click go to
display object or i'm sorry go to show
always
and
you'll see it has magazine
here the the name of the object and i
don't like that i like to clean it up a
little bit so just click that show
or display object and there we go so
i'm going to move this on the left side
so right now it doesn't actually do
anything because we haven't connected it
to our spring
so with that we need to use some
expresso so
if you click magazine
and click tags cinema 4d tags
expresso
and i've docked my espresso editor down
here just so it's easier to see on my
screen
so
let's start by actually dragging in the
magazine object into our expresso window
and
we need to create a port on here
for our magazine feeder so you can
actually do that by
if you click magazine and there's the
controls tab you can just actually drag
this magazine feeder
right down in here on this so the red
side the out port
and so we need to feed this into what
we're going to be controlling so we're
going to be controlling the squash and
stretch so drag that down in here
and
what do we want us to control inside
squash and stretch that's going to be
the factor you know
so drag that down into the input
and i could connect this directly but
we're actually going to do it a better
way with the range mapper
and the range mapper kind of tells it
can convert one value to another
for example a percentage into a degree
or
that kind of thing but uh
so just right click here go to new node
expresso calculate range mapper
and it's kind of cutting off on your
screen but
it's it's in this list
and there we have it so go ahead and
pipe the magazine feeder into the input
and under the range mapper over here on
the right
on our properties
we've got an input range and an output
range
and since we set our slider to be a
percentage
this needs to be percent so change that
there to percent
and on our squash and stretch factor
this is also a percent so inside of our
range mapper this the output range needs
to be set to percent as well
and we're going to leave the input to 0
to 100 because that's what our slider is
set to
so just leave that alone
and the output lower for example
if i go into my squash and stretch here
and change my
factor down here like this
let's just say
16 will be the lower side and
100 will be the uh we don't need to go
that high let's go 80.
so 16 and 80 is what we want to be
within so if we click on range mapper
and the lower side 16 percent
the upper side eighty percent
so now just go ahead and pipe this
together
and there we have it
if i change my magazine feeder slider
it's rigged within those ranges zero to
a hundred percent
and um i like to hide my squash and
stretch from being displayed in the
the uh the viewport just to make things
cleaner
so there we go
now the next thing we want to do is
attach the
the feeder here to the
the top of our spring
and to do that we're going to use some
some more
espresso um
so
with every spline if you click on the
spline
and then we go down to
let me
bring this down
the structure manager
you'll see that uh
each of these numbers here it correlates
to a number
to a point on our spline so
up at the top is zero and that's down
here and at the bottom 99 is at the top
and we want to connect this
feeder here to be the
where the position of this point is
so yeah like i said we're going to use
expresso and to do that we're going to
use the the point node
so if we right click go to new node
expresso general
point
and this point node is asking for the
object
and the object that we're going to plug
into the the input side here
is our spline so
just pull this in here like this
and then the output of the spline needs
to be set to object
so just click on the red
output box here and click object and
just pipe that in there
now you'll see when i click my point
node here it's it says uh it's asking
for a point index which is uh right now
it's set to zero which is the bottom
point
and if if you remember when i clicked on
my structure manager here and clicked on
99 that's the top point so
just set this to 99
and then we need to tell
expresso what to
what it's going to be controlling here
so
we're going to control the follower
and before i drag the follower into
expresso as an object it makes it a lot
easier to position
where the follower is going to be on the
spring if we put it inside of a null
object so
click on follower go to create object
null
and then that's going to make it as a
child when i hold down alt on the
keyboard
and just rename it to follower position
now if i drag this into here
so what we want to do is use the global
position on the follower so if you click
click on the
blue input port here
click on coordinates global position
and just pipe this from the point
position to the global position of the
follower
and there you go it's going to snap up
here
and it looks like it's not snapping to
the proper location because we've got
our spline is actually
um being deformed with a
deformer here
because if i click off the uh enabling
feature of the deformer you'll see that
it the spline jumps up to where it
should be
so on our point node we can actually fix
this by if we click on the point node
use deform points
and for whatever reason
it
it adds a lot more points
and
basically all you need to do is crank up
this point index until our followers at
the top of our spline so just just start
bringing this value up until the very
the top here until it doesn't go anymore
sorry right there is fine
so
right now if i were to try to move the
follower position
you can't move it because it's being
controlled by expresso and that's why i
put it inside of a
null object and now i can click on my
my subdivision surface object here and
actually move it around and reposition
it
so just kind of
centering it up within my object here
so now i should be able to
when i drag my slider it'll be
following the position of that top point
and you'll see it kind of jumps around a
bit
it's got some lag to it
that's just because of our order of
operations and priority
and one quick way to fix that if i click
on my espresso tag
you can change the priority
and uh i found that
if i put this particular one down to
generator
it'll be
solid
pretty solid there so
so yeah this the spring and the follower
is rigged
um
so let's go ahead and put the spring
and the follower inside of our
our magazine here just drag it in
and i'm going to center it up
that looks good
so yeah that's
still working great
uh the next thing i want to do is
create a bunch of clones of my bullets
here
so that uh
we can put them inside of the the
magazine
so if i click on bullet
and then come up to mograph come down to
cloner hold alt
and
click that it's going to make the bullet
a child of the cloner object
and right now it defaults to
linear the mode set to linear
and
i know there's a around 15 i think it's
cartridges inside of a magazine so if we
just bring this up to 15
then change our y
position down
to about that value
so right now they're single file you
know that that's not how they're
inserted inside of a magazine and
to uh to fix that it'd be nice to have
each one kind of offset
the way it should
and to to create an offset we're going
to use
a formula formula effector
so if we click on cloner and go up to
mograph effector
formula
uh where's it at there it is
click on formula
and it's going to do something crazy at
first but uh if we just go ahead and
zero out the formula
and then our parameter here
we don't want to change the scale so
just set this just turn this off
and
we need to
write some code in here for the formula
and i'm not
any kind of genius when it comes to to
math and and all that stuff so
um basically to
to set every other clone to be offset
we're going to use a modulo it's called
a modulo function inside cinema 4d so
to do that we just type mod and then a
parenthesis
id
semicolon
and then closing parentheses
and you'll see when i hit enter here
they're going to offset
what was it set to it was set to 50 50
centimeters we don't want to offset it
that much let's just bring this down to
to 10
just like that
so there we have that
and um
we're actually going to use two formulas
one being we're going to offset
these right bullets to the right
10 centimeters and the left side we're
going to go negative 10 centimeters
and then you'll see why i'm doing that a
little bit later but
let me just show you here
so if i click let's see here
yeah let's go ahead and add another
formula like i said so click on mograph
effector
formula
and
just zero this out
click on our cloner
and then go to the effectors tab and
drag that drag that new one in here
so that they're both working
and for this one we're gonna offset the
other ones and
i should probably show you uh
if you go into your cloner object and
click on transform it's got this display
option you can click this to index
and it shows the the number of
each clone the index number and that's
why when i did my formula here we got id
which is the index
so we got for example zero
and then two
if you want you can actually read more
about the modulo function
in cinema 4d in the help file if you
right click
the formula here and go to show help
then
you can click a list of formulas
and then yeah there's some there's a
whole bunch of information in here
regarding what the different functions
do so
i would encourage you to read that
on here's the modulo function right here
so anyway we won't go into deep
deep coding here
but um
so one formula is going to change the
offset one side and the other one's
going to change on the other side so
we got the parameter 10 centimeters we
want this formula to be
negative 10.
we don't want to affect the scale
so to make this
this particular formula we're going to
change this to equal
zero
and then the other one we're gonna
just copy this function here
paste it in and change the zero to one
so then that's gonna
offset it the way we want and if we come
back to our cloner
and bring our position wide down so that
they're touching
that's what we're looking for right
there
and i'm going to turn these uh the ids
off
the index display
so it's easier to see
so to actually change these
the position of our bullets inside of
our magazine we're gonna use
the
uh what is it the offset so
if i change the offset right now you'll
see that it's not working the way that
we'd like
we wanted to actually the bullets to
actually move
so
to do that we actually need to use a
spline object as our mode
so if we change the mode to object
it's asking for the object so if i go
into my right side view
view of the uh the magazine
click on your spline tool
and just click on
kind of a general area where you want
your
the bullets to be
cloned along so
that's about right there
go back to my perspective view
i'm gonna actually center my anchor
point to my object and i set a hotkey up
for that but just quickly do it that way
there we go
so now my anchor point is centered
within my spline
and when you create a spline it actually
creates it along the z axis if i get my
grid here
it creates it along the z axis
and this is kind of hard to explain but
basically all we need to do to fix the
positioning when we
well let me just show you
if i click on my cloner and put my
spline down here
you'll see that it does something funky
here to the bullets so if i click on my
spline and click on my
anchor point tool
we just need to rotate it on the x axis
here just uh
negative 90 degrees or 90 degrees
click off my
so this is kind of correct but now we
need to go into our cloner
under the transform and change our pitch
here the rotation pitch so if we change
this to
around negative
72 that's going to look
look correct
now we've got our bullets cloned along
our spline and you'll see our spline is
centered
within the bullets
and we have our
one formula changes the offset to the
right and and the other formula here
changes it to the left
and so if i go in my cloner object and
click on object
you'll see it my count changed from 15
to 10 we just need to change that back
to 15
and then there we go
and we just need to position these
better within the the magazine housing
to do that just click on your spline
and
just kind of position it where it should
be there
the bottom should be
yeah more or less like that
and you can actually just click on your
point tool of your spline
you can kind of you can kind of position
that fine tune it the way you want
so i'm going to go over here to the
right view and just kind of position
that a little bit better
okay so
we've got this set up so now if we
change my offset because i change this
to the an object mode
you'll see that they actually move which
is what we want but it's also now doing
something
where it's creating a another set of
bullets down here at the bottom and
that's because the loop option is
selected so if i uncheck that
and then change my offset
that's that's what we're looking for
right there so
and you'll see the that the bullets
kinda
they should be a little bit tighter knit
so if i go into my formula
parameter and change my x value here i
can kind of bring this down
each one of them
to negative 9
and that's looking a little bit better
and then i kind of want to adjust my top
point of my spline
so that these are tighter
yeah more like that
actually this should sit down kind of in
the magazine a little bit because they
don't feed out the top of the magazine
they come forward out of it so
come back to my perspective view
so
yeah our offset is set up
now all we have to do is
we can actually
control the offset with that same
the magazine feeder here the slider that
we that we set up so
to do that
just drag in your cloner object into the
espresso window
and then if we click on our offset value
bring that in as an input
we need to create a new range mapper so
right click new node
espresso calculate range mapper
and pipe the
magazine feeder
output into the input of the the range
mapper
and
remember we need to change our ranges
from
user defined to percent so just change
that to percent
and the the output is a percent because
on our cloner
offset it's set to percent
and we just want to do
zero to 100
so if we go to our range mapper
0 to 100 it's already set up so just
connect these together
and it should work
the way we want
and you'll see when it gets toward the
top here
our feeder and bullets kind of intersect
a little bit
that's because
you can actually fix this within the
range mapper the output upper just start
actually let's bring this down here
until we can see our bullet
just bring the upper
up to a value where it's touching kind
of the top where it was when we had the
uh
the slider at the bottom so
there we go
so that's like the general idea
now
i want to take this a little bit
further
and basically when the bullets get to
the top it'd be nice to have them kind
of slide into the center so that one
comes out at a time and they're not kind
of popping out the sides here
because you'll see on our our magazine
housing that it's got a tapered edge
it's kind of hard to see on my screen
but
it's got this taper
and to do that we can
use
the new fields option in in cinema 4d
let's see here
and it actually works with previous
versions of of cinema 4d as well but in
r20 they changed it to fields
as a fall off so
to do this
click on your
one of your formulas
click falloff and then linear field
and
we want it to go from top to bottom so
change this to negative y
and then we want the range to be very
small the length of it
and then position this at the top
here
so basically what this is doing is
saying
anything below this
this field
it's going to be affected by these
formula effectors and anything above the
field because it's a linear
linear i keep saying it wrong
anything above it will not be affected
so you'll see as i bring this down
they go to zero back to their default
before we're even using the formulas
and it's doing one side at a time
and we need to do it to both sides so
go ahead and create another
uh fall off for the opposite formula so
click on formula dot one linear field
and direction negative y
bring this down so it's smaller
range here
and then just bring this up
and there we go
so you'll see as i click on both these
fields here and pull them down
they're overlapping as they get to it to
the top
what i want to do is make it so when
they get toward the
the top here that they kind of push push
up and we can use
let's see here let's use
a plane effector
i'm going to pull these
fields back up
and on my plane effector
we wanted to change
the position y
so if i pull these up oops
on my actual parameter here
oh you'll see it's not doing anything
because i didn't click on my cloner
first so if i click cloner effectors and
drag my plane into the effectors window
now it's starting to work so if i click
back on my plane
and pull these down
basically i need to set up another
fall off so that affects everything
above the fall off
so to do that
click on your falloff of your plane
effector
click linear
and
this is going to be
positive y
and just change the falloff amount here
and you'll see what it's doing here
anything above is being affected and
below it is not affected so
put that here
and then
if i go into my plane effector
parameter here i'm going to bring this
up a bit
and you'll have to do some playing
around with like where this should be
positioned here on each one of these
fields
but generally
this is working a lot more
a lot like the way it should so
i noticed they're kind of pulling out
here but you can play with it and really
fine-tune fine-tune things
see they kind of each one kind of goes
one at a time
um
what else was i going to show you um
yeah i think that's working great though
oh i see
so you'll see
that my plane effector i only enabled
the
let's see here
the y value but i'd like them to pull
forward a little bit so just change the
z value
something like that
so now when i do it
they're kind of pulling forward as well
as they come out
so yeah that's pretty much it
not much to it really to be honest so
otherwise yeah it's pretty simple to
attach objects to splines with espresso
and to rig certain things with sliders
so yeah cinema 4ds it's really powerful
and
but uh like i said
if you have any questions
let me know
you can reach me on my website or just
uh shoot me an email or my twitter
channel or anything like that so anyway
i hope you guys enjoyed this tutorial
and
i'll see you next time